tsb.co.uk 2013-12-21

# TSB - Privacy

**How your personal information is used by TSB Bank plc**

**August 2013**

Please read this Privacy Notice to understand how we use and protect the information that you provide to us.

If you are a customer of the TSB Bank plc details of the information we collect and how we use it will also be set out in the terms and conditions of the product or service which you hold. In the event of a conflict between this Privacy Notice and the terms and conditions of your specific product or service, the terms and conditions of your specific product or service will take precedence.

**TSB Data Privacy Notice**   
Your information will be held by TSB Bank plc (‘TSB’).

The Data Protection Act 1998 requires us to manage all personal information in accordance with the Data Protection Principles. In particular, we are required to process your personal information fairly and lawfully. This means that you are entitled to know how we intend to use any information you provide. You can then decide whether you want to give it to us in order that we may provide the product or service that you require. All our employees are responsible for maintaining customer confidentiality. We provide training and education to all employees to remind them about their obligations. In addition, our policies and procedures are regularly audited and reviewed.

**The use of your personal data**   
Your personal data will be held by TSB. This means that once TSB is an independent company outside of Lloyds Banking Group, it will no longer share your personal data with Lloyds TSB or other Lloyds Banking Group companies unless permitted to do so under the terms of TSB’s Privacy Notice. However, data may be shared with and processed by Lloyds TSB and other Lloyds Banking Group companies until TSB leaves Lloyds Banking Group, if it is to provide assistance to you.

**Where we obtain your information**   
Your personal information will be held securely by TSB so that we (either now or in the future), can manage your relationship with us. This will include information you provide when you apply to us, and any additional information provided by you or others in various ways, including:   
a) in applications, emails and letters, during telephone calls and conversations in branch, when registering for services, in customer surveys, when you participate in competitions and promotions, through our website and during financial reviews and interviews;  
b) from analysis (for example, the amount, frequency, location, origin and recipient) of your payments and other transactions, from your use of our services and what we know from operating your account; and   
c) information we receive from our business partners and from other organisations such as credit reference agencies and fraud prevention agencies.

We will not retain your personal information for longer than is necessary for the maintenance of your account, or for legal or regulatory requirements.

If you give us personal information about someone else (such as a joint applicant) then you should not do so without their permission. Where information is provided by you about someone else, or someone else discloses information about you, it may be added to any personal information that is already held by us and it will be used in the ways described in this Privacy Notice.

**How we use your information**   
We may use the personal information we hold about you for the following administrative activities:   
a) providing you with products and services and notifying you about either important changes or developments to the features and operation of those products and services;   
b) responding to your enquiries and complaints;   
c) administering offers, competitions and promotions;  
d) undertaking financial reviews;

and also for the following data processing activities:   
e) updating, consolidating, and improving the accuracy of our records;   
f) undertaking transactional analysis;   
g) arrears and debt recovery activities;   
h) testing new systems and checking upgrades to existing systems;   
i) crime detection, prevention, and prosecution;   
j) evaluating the effectiveness of marketing and for market research and training;   
k) customer modelling, statistical and trend analysis, with the aim of developing and improving products and services;   
l) assessing lending and insurance risks;   
m) managing your relationship with us.

By processing this information – it enables us to better understand your needs and run your accounts in the efficient way that you expect.

Your data may also be used for other purposes for which you give your specific permission, or, in very limited circumstances, when required by law or where permitted under the terms of the Data Protection Act.

**When we may share your information**   
We will treat your personal information as private and confidential, but may disclose it outside TSB if:   
a) allowed by this agreement;   
b) you consent;   
c) needed by our agents, advisors or others involved in running accounts and services for you or collecting what you owe us;   
d) needed by subcontractors to help us manage your records;   
e) HM Revenue & Customs or other authorities require it;   
f) the law, regulatory bodies or the public interest permits or requires it;   
g) required by us or others to investigate or prevent crime;   
h) needed by market research companies to assist us in providing better products and services for you;   
i) if needed by any other parties connected with your account (including guarantors); or   
j) required as part of our duty to protect your accounts, for example we are required to disclose your information to the UK Financial Services Compensation Scheme (FSCS).

We will always ensure your information remains safe and secure.

**Using your information to help prevent terrorism and crime**   
The Government also requires us to screen applications that are made to us to ensure we are complying with the international fight against terrorism and other criminal activities. As a result of this we may need to disclose information to government bodies.

**Sharing your information to assist with asset buying or selling**   
We may in the future wish to sell, transfer or merge part or all of our business or assets, or any associated rights or interests, or to acquire a business or enter into a merger with it. If so, we may disclose your personal information to a potential buyer, transferee, or merger partner or seller and their advisers so long as they agree to keep it confidential and to use it only to consider the possible transaction. If the transaction goes ahead, the buyers, transferee or merger partner may use or disclose your personal information in the same way as set out in this notice.

**Sharing your personal information with credit card providers**   
If you hold a credit or debit card with us, we will share transaction details with our scheme providers (e.g. Visa or MasterCard).

**Sharing your personal information between first and second charge lenders**   
If you have a secured loan or mortgage with us, we may need to share information with other lenders who also hold a charge on your property.

**Sharing personal information between joint applicants**   
Sometimes, when you open a joint account or product, this may mean that your personal data will be shared with the other applicant. For example, transactions made by you will be seen by your joint account holder and vice versa.

**How we use credit reference agencies and fraud prevention agencies**

**Credit Reference Agencies**   
Credit Reference Agencies (CRAs) collect and maintain information about consumers' and businesses' credit behaviour. This includes Electoral Register, fraud prevention, and credit information – including details of previous applications and the conduct of your accounts – and public information such as County Court Judgements, decrees, and bankruptcies.

The information that we and other organisations provide to credit reference agencies about you, your financial associates and your business (if you have one) may be provided to other organisations and used by them and us to:   
a) help make decisions, for example when:   
  (i) checking details on applications for credit and credit-related or other facilities;   
  (ii) managing credit and credit-related accounts or facilities;   
  (iii) recovering debt;   
  (iv) checking details on proposals and claims for all types of insurance;   
  (v) checking details of job applicants and employees;   
b) detect and prevent crime, fraud and money laundering;   
c) check your credit history;   
d) verify your identity if you, or someone financially linked with you, applies for services;   
e) trace your whereabouts; and   
f) undertake research, statistical analysis and systems testing.

If we need to make a credit decision when you apply for a service (e.g. mortgage, personal loan, credit card or current account) or to review the amount of credit we provide under an existing agreement, such as an overdraft, your records will be searched along with those of anyone who is financially associated with you such as your spouse or partner. The CRA will keep a record of this search and place a “footprint” on your credit file, whether or not the application proceeds.

The Data Protection Act does not generally apply to companies but it does cover personal data relating to sole traders and partnerships. When we receive an application from a business we may perform a search with a credit reference agency on the individual company directors or partners, or any guarantors.

We may also give details of your account and how you conduct it to credit reference agencies, including if you borrow and do not repay in full and on time. If you fall behind with your payments and a full payment or satisfactory proposals are not received within 28 days of a formal demand being issued, then a default notice may be recorded with the CRAs. Similar information may also be given about your other lending/credit relationships with us. Any records shared with CRAs will remain on file for 6 years after your account is closed, whether it has been settled by you or as a result of a default. Other organisations may see these searches and updates if you apply for credit in the future, and these may affect your ability to borrow from other lenders.

If you apply for or hold an account in joint names, or tell us that you have a spouse or financial associate, a financial association will be created between your records, including any previous and subsequent names used by you. This means that your financial affairs may be treated as affecting each other. These links will remain on your and their files until such time as you or your partner is successful in applying for a disassociation with the CRAs to break that link. You must be sure that you have their agreement to disclose information about them. Searches may be made on all joint applicants, and search footprints will be left on all applicants’ records.

You have a right to apply to the credit reference agencies for a copy of your file. We carry out most of our credit searches using Experian, but details of how you have run your account(s) may be disclosed to all the credit reference agencies. The information they hold may not be the same and there is a small fee that you may need to pay to each agency that you apply to. Their addresses are:

  * Experian Consumer Help Service, PO Box 9000, Nottingham NG80 7WP or call 

  * 0844 481 8000 or log on to [www.experian.co.uk](http://www.experian.co.uk/ "Experian Credit Agency \(opens in a new browser window\)")

  * Equifax plc, Credit File Advice Centre, PO Box 1140, Bradford BD1 5US or log on to [www.myequifax.co.uk](http://www.myequifax.co.uk/ "My Equifax \(Opens in a new window\)")

  * CallCredit, Consumer Services Team, PO Box 491, Leeds LS3 1WZ or call 0870 060 1414 or log on to [www.callcredit.co.uk](http://www.callcredit.co.uk/ "Call Credit \(Opens in new window\)")

**Fraud Prevention Agencies**   
We have systems that protect our customers and ourselves against fraud and other crime. Customer information can be used to prevent crime and trace those responsible. We will share your personal information from your application with fraud prevention agencies. If false or inaccurate information is provided and fraud is identified, details of this fraud will be passed to these agencies. Law enforcement agencies may access and use this information. We and other organisations may also access and use this information to prevent fraud and money laundering, for example, when:

  * checking details on applications for credit and credit related or other facilities; 

  * managing credit and credit related accounts or facilities; 

  * recovering debt; 

  * checking details on proposals and claims for all types of insurance; 

  * checking details of job applicants and employees. 

Please contact us on 0845 835 7899 if you want to receive details of the relevant fraud prevention agencies. We and other organisations may access and use from other countries the information recorded by fraud prevention agencies.

**How we manage information collected on credit card statements**   
Some transactions that you or an additional card holder makes on a card account may cause sensitive or confidential details to appear on your statement. By using your card to make such transactions you give us your explicit consent to process this information.

**Using companies to process your information outside the EEA**   
All countries in the European Economic Area (EEA), which includes the UK, have similar standards of legal protection for your personal information. We may run your accounts and provide other services from centres outside the EEA (such as the USA and India) that do not have a similar standard of data protection laws to the UK. If so, we will require your personal information to be protected to at least UK standards.

We may process payments through other financial institutions such as banks and the worldwide payments system operated by the SWIFT organisation if, for example, you make a CHAPS payment or a foreign payment. Those external organisations may process and store your personal information abroad and may have to disclose it to foreign authorities to help them in their fight against crime and terrorism. If these are based outside the EEA, your personal information may not be protected to standards similar to those in the UK.

**How we may contact you**

**Using your personal information to contact you about products and services**   
Unless you have asked us not to, we may contact you by mail, telephone, email or text message about products and services available from us. In addition we may also contact you about products and services from other selected companies, which we believe may be of interest to you or benefit you financially.

We promise not to contact you about everything – only if we think it could be appropriate and relevant to you, such as preferential savings opportunities, account upgrades or special offers. This contact may continue after your relationship with us ends. You may opt out of receiving information at any time by calling us, writing to us or contacting your local branch.

**Passing your information to other companies for their own direct marketing**   
Unless you have given us your consent, we will not provide information about you to other companies to use for their own marketing purposes.

**Using your email address for service contact**   
Making sure we deliver excellent customer service is very important to us and to do this various methods of communication may be used when sending you information about your account. Most of the time you will be contacted by letter or telephone, but you may also be sent updates by text message or email when it is believed to be appropriate. You can ask us to stop sending these messages at any time. Additionally, in extraordinary circumstances (such as natural disaster or civil unrest) we may also send you updates by text message or email. If we decide to use email to contact you, we will only do this if we have ensured that using email will not put your information at risk, or, if you have requested we email you, that we have explained the risks of sending an "insecure" email and that you are happy to accept that risk.

In addition you may wish to choose a channel of communication that suits you when you need to contact us. If you need to email us, we recommend you check our website to see if a secure email facility exists so that your email can be sent securely. If you send us emails in other ways, such as from your personal account, then remember that the message may not be secure and there is a risk that it could be intercepted. If you choose to send an "insecure" email, please keep the amount of confidential information you include to a minimum.

**When you apply for and use our products and services**

**Using credit scoring**   
When you apply for credit, an automated system known as credit scoring may be used when considering whether to agree the borrowing. It is a method of assessing your likely conduct of an account based on a range of data, including the conduct of previous similar accounts. It is a system widely used by credit providers to help make fair and informed decisions on lending.

Credit scoring takes account of information from three sources – the information you provide on your application, information provided by credit reference agencies and information that may already be held about you by us. A credit scoring system will consider information from these sources, to make an overall assessment of your application. The credit scoring methods used are regularly tested to ensure they remain fair, effective and unbiased.

Using a credit scoring system helps us to lend responsibly. If you submit an application and it is declined through this automated process, you can contact us within 21 days to have the decision reconsidered. You also have the right to ask that the decision is not made based solely using a credit scoring system.

**Searching insurance records**   
If you apply to us for insurance, we will pass your details to the insurer. If you make a claim, any information you give to us, or to the insurer, may be put onto a register of claims and shared with other insurers to prevent fraudulent claims. A list of the participants is available from the insurer. We may also disclose your information to our agents and other insurers to investigate or prevent fraud.

**How we manage sensitive personal information**   
The Data Protection Act defines certain information as ‘sensitive’ (racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious beliefs, trade union membership, physical or mental health, sexual life, criminal proceedings and offences). If you apply to us for insurance we may ask you for some ‘sensitive’ information, but we will always ask for your explicit consent. As a customer, there may also be times when you give us 'sensitive' information. We will use it to provide the service you require and may share it with our subcontractors to keep our records up to date.

**How we check your identity**   
We may ask you to provide physical forms of identity verification when you open your account. Alternatively, we may search credit reference agency files in assessing your application. The agency also gives us other details and information from the Electoral Register to verify your identity. The agency keeps a record of our search, whether or not your application proceeds. Our search is not seen or used by lenders to assess your ability to obtain credit.

**Undertaking anti-money laundering checks**   
To comply with money laundering regulations, there are times when we need to confirm (or reconfirm) the name and address of our customers. For more details about identity checks, please refer to What proof of identity can I use?

**Obtaining information about you, and other personal details**   
When you apply for a mortgage or further borrowing it may be necessary to obtain references, details of your existing financial commitments, and any other information that is required to assess or review lending risks, to recover debts, and to prevent or detect fraud. Where applicable, your current and previous employers, accountant, landlord, lender, bank, insurance or pension company may be contacted to obtain this information. In limited circumstances these references may need to be obtained after you open your account. This may be for regulatory purposes, or if the lending decision needs to be reviewed. Your permission to obtain these references will therefore continue to apply after your account has been opened. It may also be necessary to obtain information or documentation from your solicitor relating to any work they carry out either on your or our behalf.

**Recording phone calls**   
We may monitor or record phone calls with you in case we need to check we have carried out your instructions correctly, to resolve queries or issues, for regulatory purposes, to help improve our quality of service, and to help detect or prevent fraud or other crimes. Conversations may also be monitored for staff training purposes.

**Using information on social networking sites**   
As part of our ongoing commitment to understanding our customers better, we may research comments and opinions made public on social networking sites such as Twitter and Facebook.

**Obtaining a copy of your information**   
Under the Data Protection Act you have the right of access to your personal data. The Act allows us to charge a fee of £10 for this service. If anything is inaccurate or incorrect, please let us know and we will correct it. For further details on how to request a copy of your information, please contact:

**DSAR Unit,  
TSB Bank plc   
Ariel House,   
2138 Coventry Road,   
Sheldon,   
Birmingham   
B26 3JW **

**Cookies**   
In general, you can visit our website without identifying who you are or revealing any information about yourself. However, cookies are used to store small amounts of information on your computer, which allows certain information from your web browser to be collected. Cookies are widely used on the internet and do not identify the individual using the computer, just the computer being used. Cookies and other similar technology make it easier for you to log on to and use our websites during future visits.

To access our cookie notice, please go to http://www.tsb.co.uk/cookie_policy.asp

**Changes to privacy notice**   
We keep our Privacy Notice under regular review and we will reflect any updates within this notice.

This Privacy Notice was issued in August 2013.

**Further information**   
For further information please contact your local branch.
